<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Councillor Zeeshan Hamid</title>
    <description>Milton and Halton Councillor Zeeshan Hamid</description>
    <link>https://zeehamid.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://zeehamid.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2019 22:12:33 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2019 22:12:33 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Milton passes a 2.86% overall tax increase on the local budget increase of 5.68%</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The Town of Milton continues to be the lowest-taxed jurisdiction, with property taxes well below other municipalities in the surrounding area. 
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.ibb.co/QD6nYTQ/ELc-YTz-DW4-AAUGGa.png&quot; alt=&quot;Milton&#39;s rate compared to other municipalities&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facing a challenging budget, the council passed an &lt;strong&gt;overall tax increase of 2.86%&lt;/strong&gt; based on Milton’s budget increase of 5.63%. This allowed the council to reverse cuts to tree plantings, delays in park construction, protect the community fund and save Saturday transit. The budget also continues to set aside money for infrastructure reserves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“This budget makes important investments in both services and infrastructure in our community.” &lt;br /&gt;
Budget Chair, Councillor Mike Cluett&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The budget spends $78M in capital projects, the majorty of these in roads based on the feedback from residents. This includes roadway expansions such as Thompson Road (Britannia Road to Louis St. Laurent Avenue), Louis St. Laurent Avenue (Fourth Line to James Snow Parkway), Fifth Line (Hwy 401 to Derry Road) and Bronte Street (Main Street to Steeles Avenue). Increased funding will go towards maintenance and rehabilitation of existing roadways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I’m greatly encouraged that council withstood the temptation to dip further into  reserves as a method of funding operating costs.”&lt;br /&gt;
Ward 3 Councillor Rick Di Lorenzo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2020, a fifth Fire Station is planned to open near Regional Road 25 and Louis St. Laurent and the Sherwood Community Centre will celebrate its first full year of operation. These new facilities help to maintain and deliver important services to Milton’s growing community. Based on the Youth Strategy recommendations, approved in 2019, the Town will also implement a pilot project in 2020 focusing on youth-specific spaces and programming at facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Milton is a great place to live. This budget maintains our tax advantage while protecting services our residents have come to rely on.”&lt;br /&gt;
Councillor Zeeshan Hamid&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to protecting key services, the council also supported Councillor Sameera Ali’s motion to bring forward Bowes Neighbourhood Community Park in ward 4 by 4 years and Councillor Zeeshan Hamid’s motion to add windrow cleaning for all seniors and people of disability who were on the long wating list. Councillor Hamid’s motion of not cutting tree plantings down by 300 (from 750) was also supported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end, the budget did not receive the approval of Mayor Krantz and Councillors Best and Malbeouf, who all wanted to see further cuts to bring the local share down from 5.63% to 5%. “That represents less than a dollar a month”, said Councillor Hamid, voicing his concern that “bringing the rate down to that level requires cutting Saturday transit and the community fund, or cutting the Moffat park redevelopment completely. How can you tell people they don’t get the services they rely on to save less than a buck.”  Councillor Sameera Ali expressed her satisfaction that the budget supported significant infrastructure programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I am happy that we are moving forward with a budget that brings us closer to filling the growth and infrastructure gap.”&lt;br /&gt;
Councillor Sameera Ali&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final budget passed with a vote of 6-3. For the average single detached home in Milton, the Town’s 2020 budget will result in an additional $88.21 per year ($7.35 per month).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thoughts? Let me know: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:zee.hamid@milton.ca&quot;&gt;zee.hamid@milton.ca&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2019 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://zeehamid.com/2019/12/10/milton-passes-a-286-tax-increase.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://zeehamid.com/2019/12/10/milton-passes-a-286-tax-increase.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>milton</category>
        
        <category>information</category>
        
        <category>taxes</category>
        
        <category>services</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Breakdown Of Your Property Taxes</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I hope this is shared widely because there’s a lot of misinformation out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Curious to know how your property tax dollars are distributed in Milton? This chart should help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please keep in mind that this only includes tax-supported spending (most spending is paid for by provincial subsidies, user fees, development charges, grants, etc that isn’t shown here). I also lumped some categories for simplicity, otherwise the chart became too wide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://zeehamid.com/images/property-taxes.png&quot; alt=&quot;Property tax breakdown&quot; /&gt;
Expand: &lt;a href=&quot;https://zeehamid.com/images/property-taxes.png&quot;&gt;https://zeehamid.com/images/property-taxes.png&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thoughts? Let me know: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:zee.hamid@milton.ca&quot;&gt;zee.hamid@milton.ca&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2019 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://zeehamid.com/2019/12/05/breakdown-of-your-property-taxes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://zeehamid.com/2019/12/05/breakdown-of-your-property-taxes.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>milton</category>
        
        <category>information</category>
        
        <category>taxes</category>
        
        <category>services</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Taxes and Services - How to Balance</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thoughts on new ways of looking at Milton’s taxes?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you keep hearing, Milton has the lowest taxes in GTA by far. In fact, we are 30% below the average of neighbouring municipalities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It creates a challenge where we’re unable to provide similar services without raiding our reserves and risking our future financial health. In fact, raiding reserves is something the council will likely do again next month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our staff is recommending a better (IMO) approach, one I’ve argued for in the past as well since I prefer concrete, measurable (and achievable) goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set a goal of staying 15% below the lower of Burlington and Halton Hills (which both have low taxes themselves). That’s a reasonable way of saying we’re “efficient” at providing services.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add an additional goal to provide each service at a cost that’s 20% below the average of other municipalities. This gives you a measurable way of ensuring we’re efficient.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The combination of the two will 1) keep our taxes low, 2) provide services you deserve, and 3) demonstrate that we’re providing each service in a very cost-effective way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current approach of driving taxes as low as possible no matter what the cost isn’t working. It’s taking us to a financial disaster where every analysis shows that we will not be able to maintain all the roads and parks we have developers build using development charges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thoughts? Let me know: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:zee.hamid@milton.ca&quot;&gt;zee.hamid@milton.ca&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I am not adding a poll intentionally since I am more interested in hearing your thoughts).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2019 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://zeehamid.com/2019/11/19/taxes-and-services.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://zeehamid.com/2019/11/19/taxes-and-services.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>survey</category>
        
        <category>opinion</category>
        
        <category>taxes</category>
        
        <category>services</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lead in municipal water</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Some of you have asked me and other councillors questions about media reports that found lead in water. Here are some details from the regional staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t speak for others, but in Halton region the potential for lead in our drinking water system is extremely low. In fact, we have one of the highest compliance ratings – over 99% compliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our high compliance rating is a result of all the proactive and continuous measures Halton Region has taken over the past decade to ensure we are delivering the safest and highest quality drinking water possible. In 2007, the Region undertook a Cast Iron Watermain Replacement Program. This program identified and replaced all old cast iron watermains in Halton Region, while at the same time replacing all known lead public service lines and connections. Since that time, all known public lead service lines and connections have been replaced. As part of our continuous monitoring, we investigate the neighborhood for the presence of lead as part of any watermain project or at the time of a water main break. If lead is observed, Halton Region takes immediate corrective action and replaces the service line or connection. Since the Cast Iron Watermain Replacement Program was completed, lead services have been observed 3 times within the public right-of-way and those services were removed. Moreover, if a lead service line was observed, on private property, the homeowners were notified and provided with guidance on private side corrective actions required (e.g., replacement of private service lines and indoor plumbing, or flushing).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to these programs, we have been helping homeowners check for the presence of lead to ensure safe drinking water:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;· Halton has recently replaced over 14,000 water meters in older areas of Halton Region as part of the Pulse Water Meter Replacement Program. Of the 14,000 homes that have had their meter replaced through the program, no private water services was observed to be lead.· We will continue to look for the presence of lead water services on the private property side through the upcoming Advanced Meter Replacement (AMI) program, where all homes will be required to have their meters upgraded or replaced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Halton’s drinking water is safe and the risk of lead is very low, there may be lead in the water from pipe fittings and connections in older homes (e.g. build prior to the 1960’s). We are helping to educate residents on how to check their plumbing. If a resident has any concerns, we will be sending a Halton representative to check their connections and provide guidance on corrective actions required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I would like to confirm that students were not exposed to water that exceeded the Provincial limit for lead at White Oaks Secondary School in Oakville. The 140 µg/L level reported in the Globe and Mail was the result from a standing water sample taken during the summer. This test occurred before the school opened for the school year, corrective actions were taken as part of the requirements and resampling of flushed water (water that would be consumed) was within the acceptable provincial limit for lead. School Boards are responsible under the Safe Drinking Water Act, 2002 to conduct regular lead testing, pipe flushing and pipe replacements to ensure the safety of the water within schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The health and safety of our residents is our number one priority. We will continue our surveillance measures and control programs to ensure we meet the drinking water quality standards and provide our residents with the assurance that our water is high quality and safe to drink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you and please let me know if you have any questions,&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2019 14:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://zeehamid.com/2019/11/06/lead-in-municipal-water.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://zeehamid.com/2019/11/06/lead-in-municipal-water.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>announcement</category>
        
        <category>lead</category>
        
        <category>water</category>
        
        <category>safety</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Welcome to my new site</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After 10+ years of a WordPress-based site with 400+ blog posts, I’ve decided to redo my site as static HTML pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found that the WordPress site slowed down over time. My options were to pay even more for a beefier hosting, or re-create the site using static HTML. I opted for option #2. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The end result is that the new site is 20x faster and best of all, I get to host it for free (hosting on github, since some people asked). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided not to migrate old posts to this site. Instead, I archived them here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://zeehamid4.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;https://zeehamid4.wordpress.com/&lt;/a&gt; . If you have an old link to a specific post then it will be redirected automatically. New posts will be published on this site. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope you enjoy it. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2019 02:49:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://zeehamid.com/2019/06/24/welcome-to-my-new-site.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://zeehamid.com/2019/06/24/welcome-to-my-new-site.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>announcement</category>
        
        <category>wordpress</category>
        
        <category>Jekyll</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
